<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Lorena Mesa</title><link href="http://lorenamesa.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://lorenamesa.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://lorenamesa.com/</id><updated>2019-07-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>My checklist to hosting an inclusive event</title><link href="http://lorenamesa.com/my-checklist-to-hosting-an-inclusive-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-07-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2019-07-27:/my-checklist-to-hosting-an-inclusive-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having been a community organizer in several regards over the years, a common question I am asked is "How do I run an event?". To which I respond, "Here is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having been a community organizer in several regards over the years, a common question I am asked is "How do I run an event?". To which I respond, "Here is how I run an inclusive event". My intent is not to sound smart when I insert the emphasis on inclusivity, but to highlight inclusivity as the overarching theme when building community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What do I mean when I say inclusivity?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we discuss inclusivity, you may hear it bundled in such phrases as "diversity and inclusion" or "diversity, inclusion, and belonging". Inclusivity, as I understand it, cannot occur without consideration to the diversity or belonging of its community members. Inclusivity relies on both the rich, diverse backgrounds (e.g. ethnicity, country of origin, language, sexuality) of its members but more importantly on the extent that those members have a sense of acceptance and belonging. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it in other terms, "diversity is being invited to the party, inclusion is being asked to dance" (as I heard it described at PyCon Colombia 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Community building begins with inclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a list of things I have developed over the years, with the full acknowledgement that some of these at times can be aspirational:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host at a venue that &lt;a href="https://www.adachecklist.org/doc/fullchecklist/ada-checklist.pdf"&gt;ADA compliant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure presenters create presentations with &lt;a href="https://github.com/A11YChi/A11Y-Presentations"&gt;accessibility in mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Require that the host venue use RSVPed names bypassing the need to use &lt;a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/transgender/deadnaming"&gt;a name on an ID&lt;/a&gt; (as these are often out of sync anyway)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a clearly placed &lt;a href="https://geekfeminism.wikia.org/wiki/Code_of_conduct_evaluations"&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt; on the community page (e.g. see our &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Chicago-PyLadies/"&gt;about section&lt;/a&gt;), kicking off each event with a reminder to the Code of Conduct and to seek organizers if there are any questions/concerns/feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce myself at the start of each event with my name and &lt;a href="http://feministing.com/2015/02/03/how-using-they-as-a-singular-pronoun-can-change-the-world/"&gt;pronouns&lt;/a&gt; (ideally having some mechanism for attendees to mark pronouns such as on name tags if worn) to set community norms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I highly recommend that all organizers participate in a Code of Conduct training, learning how to respond to incident reports and brainstorming ways to develop procedure if one is lacking or incomplete. There are several groups, such as &lt;a href="https://otter.technology/code-of-conduct-training/"&gt;Otter Tech&lt;/a&gt;, that offer training as well as &lt;a href="https://geekfeminism.wikia.org/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment"&gt;many resources available online&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are seeking likeminded organizers to discuss inclusivity with the &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Diversity_and_Inclusion_for_Communities_and_Contributors"&gt;Mozilla Diverstiy and Inclusion for COmmunities and Contributors group&lt;/a&gt; is a rich community with an email list for discussion and semi-frequent scheduled calls to discuss specific topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How we can do better?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As inclusivisity is always a work in progress, I actively solicit feedback by asking, "How can we do better?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What tools, community norms and practices, requirements do you use when hosting an inclusive event? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, how can we do better?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="inclusion"></category><category term="inclusivity"></category><category term="community-building"></category><category term="diversity"></category><category term="belonging"></category></entry><entry><title>Building a GitHub page with Pelican, a Python static site generator</title><link href="http://lorenamesa.com/building-a-github-page-with-pelican-a-python-static-site-generator.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2018-08-28:/building-a-github-page-with-pelican-a-python-static-site-generator.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've ever wanted to quickly spin up a personal website but, like me, are either preoccupied with design or want something basic to help you get started look no …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've ever wanted to quickly spin up a personal website but, like me, are either preoccupied with design or want something basic to help you get started look no further. Static site generators are a great way to help you build a website if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you want to use a predefined css/html template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don't want to deal with a complicated dynamic CMS like Wordpress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;want a page that will be served up fast!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;are looking to add version control to your content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code behind my website is powered by &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a Python static website generator. If you are curious about other static website generators, there are various &lt;a href="https://www.creativebloq.com/features/10-best-static-site-generators"&gt;lists&lt;/a&gt; on the web that you can easily find with a Google search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do I build a website with Pelican?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, I'll cover how to build a GitHub page website with Pelican that is hosted on (surprise surprise) GitHub. Additionally we'll review how to add version control to your GitHub repo that maintains the website content, the website theme, and Pelican code in separate repos. Lastly, we'll deploy the code to the GitHub page and even customize the GitHub page with a domain name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll likely want to clone a copy &lt;a href="https://github.com/lorenanicole/lorenanicole.github.io-src"&gt;my repo&lt;/a&gt; to follow along with the code snippets in this post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download the code to your machine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git clone --recursive repo-url  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# downloads the submodules&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What's in the repo?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master (&lt;code&gt;lorenanicole.github.io-src&lt;/code&gt;) repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;/output&lt;/code&gt; dir points to &lt;a href="https://github.com/lorenanicole/lorenannicole.github.io"&gt;my GitHub pages repo&lt;/a&gt; where Pelican builds and stores generated static files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;'/voce' dir points to &lt;a href="https://github.com/lorenanicole/voce"&gt;fork of the Pelican theme voce&lt;/a&gt; used in my website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find more Pelican themes explore &lt;a href="http://www.pelicanthemes.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need help configuring your own Pelican repos? Read &lt;a href="https://fedoramagazine.org/make-github-pages-blog-with-pelican/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Generating content&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pelican theme (in this case &lt;code&gt;voce&lt;/code&gt;) has templates that define the design of the website. The customizations for configuring a Pelican website are found in the &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt; file in this repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create content add a Markdown or RST file with the name of the page or article you'd like to create. Markdown, as used in this repo, will need to be installed via &lt;code&gt;pip install Markdown&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write an article create a &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.rst&lt;/code&gt; file in the &lt;code&gt;/content/articles&lt;/code&gt; directory. You'll need to specify a title at a minimum, other attributes can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write a page, again create create a &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.rst&lt;/code&gt; file, this time in the &lt;code&gt;/content/pages&lt;/code&gt; directory. Again you need to specify minimum metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your pages (the site navigation sections defined in the menu) or articles (e.g. blog posts) are created you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;make html &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; make serve  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Exports static pages/articles to /output and serves locally&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If all looks good you can: &lt;code&gt;make publish&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;make html&lt;/code&gt; but ensure your &lt;code&gt;SITE_URL&lt;/code&gt; is set to not to &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /output
git remote -v  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ensure points to the github page repo&lt;/span&gt;
git add 
git commit -m &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;new pages&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
git push
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;code&gt;yourusername.github.io&lt;/code&gt; to see the changes real time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an entire overview of getting started with Pelican read the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.1.1/getting_started.html"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you add your own domain to your github page?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to add a &lt;code&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; file with your domain name in your github pages repo. Additionally you'll need to configure your DNS record on your domain provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples tutorials:
- &lt;a href="http://spector.io/how-to-set-up-github-pages-with-a-custom-domain-on-gandi/"&gt;Gandi + GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;
- &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@supriyakankure/how-to-add-a-custom-domain-to-your-github-page-with-godaddy-84495781143e"&gt;GoDaddy + GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Questions?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please reach out! All my contact info is in the menu above. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="github-page"></category></entry></feed>