<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Lorena Mesa</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://lorenamesa.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://lorenamesa.com/</id><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>What is your voting plan? Or, how my plan is to follow Michelle Obama into hell</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/what-is-your-voting-plan.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2020-08-17:/what-is-your-voting-plan.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week marks the 100th year anniversary of the 19th Amendment in the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.archives.gov/files/exhibits/featured-documents/amendment-19/images/kaiser-wilson-l.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; 100 years, women (and to be clear not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; women, because …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week marks the 100th year anniversary of the 19th Amendment in the United States of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.archives.gov/files/exhibits/featured-documents/amendment-19/images/kaiser-wilson-l.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; 100 years, women (and to be clear not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; women, because, history, and that's a topic for another post) whom were citizens in the United States of America gained the right to vote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right of citizens of the United States to vote shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any State on account of sex. Congress shall have power to enforce this article by appropriate legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only fitting that Michelle Obama should sport a &lt;code&gt;VOTE&lt;/code&gt; necklace during her empassioned virtual Democratic National Convention address tonight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.cnn.com/cnnnext/dam/assets/200817232549-michelle-obama-vote-necklace-exlarge-169.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Voting during COVID19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voting in a normal year is always fraught with issues, from disinterest and apathy to the normal run of the mill attack on civil liberties. However, add in 2020 and we are seeing an entire new threshold of issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the very real physical danger of voting in person due to the novel coronavirus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;baseless and malicious attacks from &lt;a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/08/03/trump-nevada-mail-voting-lawsuit-390878"&gt;Trump and his campaign alleging mailin voting is illegal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.wttw.com/2020/08/16/pelosi-call-house-back-session-vote-usps-bill"&gt;the precarious fiscial situation of the United States Postal Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;social media tech giants unwillingness (or at leasts low response) &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/12/technology/google-facebook-coalition-us-election.html"&gt;to tackle "fake news" and conspiracy theories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the overall relentless attacks against vulnerable communities, but particularly POC communities, ranging from being &lt;a href="https://www.wbez.org/stories/a-perfect-storm-50-lives-and-4-zip-codes-tell-chicagos-story-of-covid-19-inequality/50b822ae-523e-47fa-a823-3c6a1c3ee12f"&gt;the most vulernable to COVID19&lt;/a&gt; to police brutality to food and &lt;a href="https://www.housingstudies.org/blog/Examining-the-Neighborhood-Level-Impact-of-COVID/"&gt;rent insecurity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collectively, these challenges add an even finer point to why voting matter -- &lt;em&gt;if we don't show up, what else will we lose?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making a voting plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;exhausting&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;overwhelming&lt;/em&gt; to discuss things in 2020. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, you are not alone. We all are here. Trying to figure out how to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way we can move forward towards Election 2020 is to prepare, plan, and be ready. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details &lt;a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/specials/plan-your-vote-state-by-state-guide-voting-by-mail-early-in-person-voting-election/"&gt;vary state to state&lt;/a&gt; and states are scrambling to clarify what date a mail in ballot &lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/2020/07/13/889751095/signed-sealed-undelivered-thousands-of-mail-in-ballots-rejected-for-tardiness"&gt;can be accepted&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how are you planning to vote? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter in our need to &lt;a href="https://www.ncjw.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/Create-a-Voting-Plan.pdf"&gt;prepare a voting plan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, of the more than 120 million votes cast only &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/2016-election/swing-state-margins/"&gt;some 107,000 votes in three states effectively decided the election&lt;/a&gt;. This math is beyond problematic. Why we continue to have an electoral college which disproportionately gives states with less population more voting power (cough: Senate) &lt;a href="https://www.sceneonradio.org/episode-31-turning-the-lens-seeing-white-part-1/"&gt;is an oddity in the simplest of terms&lt;/a&gt;. In order to take on strucutral inequities, we need to take action to install a competent Executive body that believes, in no particular order: the value of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; but particularly those whom have suffered harm so unjustly for so long, science, truth, decency, and above all &lt;em&gt;in us&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's make this voting plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's three questions I want you answer for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will you vote?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will you confirm you have voted?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If that fails, what will your backup be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of y'all already answered me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Registered! Got the receipt and know all my voting location and mail-in ballot drop-offs. Everyone should check their registrations as well as know their voting locations.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; mrcartoonster 🇺🇸🇵🇷 (@mrcartoonster) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mrcartoonster/status/1295559663493107712?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Just confirmed my voting registration and mailing address. Also got text alerts setup so I know when my ballot is mailed to me and received. I plan to take my ballot to a local drop site 👍🏻&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; RedBear (@gizm0_0) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gizm0_0/status/1295560853593264128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's where I need your help. It's not enough to plan only for yourself. You need to find ways to hold yourself accountable. As well as others in your circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps I've taken:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confirmed I'm registered by mail to vote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confirmed I have PTO for November 3 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Confirmed where my nearest voting precict is in the case my ballot is late&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You've got homework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go and ask five folks in your network. That's your homework. Do it. If not for me, then for Michelle Obama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;My voting plan, in so many words, as wordsmithed by a colleague named Kevin. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/DNC2020convention?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#DNC2020convention&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/CAEZ3Ujvds"&gt;pic.twitter.com/CAEZ3Ujvds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; Mesa @ #BlackLivesMatter 🖤 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1295561304007233536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/2020/8/18/21373174/michelle-obama-dnc-speech-trump"&gt;She deserves better&lt;/a&gt;. I do. And yes, so do you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Oh yah ...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started a crowdsourced daily digest over at &lt;a href="http://wtdtodayelection2020.us/"&gt;What To Do Today Election 2020&lt;/a&gt; with daily news, events, call to action, and whatever else we need. Subscribe! Read it! Suggest content! &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Voting"></category><category term="Election-2020"></category></entry><entry><title>Your Bias And Equity in Tech Reading Starter Pack</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/your-bias-and-equity-in-tech-reading-starter-pack.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-06-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-06-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2020-06-14:/your-bias-and-equity-in-tech-reading-starter-pack.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Increasingly we use our biometric data to power the tech we use in our day to day lives. From using our face to unlock our smart phones to using &lt;a href="https://www.clearme.com/how-it-works/"&gt;our …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Increasingly we use our biometric data to power the tech we use in our day to day lives. From using our face to unlock our smart phones to using &lt;a href="https://www.clearme.com/how-it-works/"&gt;our fingerprints for air travel&lt;/a&gt;, technology has enabled us to track and survey peoples at an alarming rate. Often in ways that are invisible to us and without our consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, survelliance and its problematic relationship to technology is not new.
Since the launch of Amazon's facial recognition software - &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/rekognition/"&gt;Rekognition&lt;/a&gt; - it has been subject to severe questioning. Especially as Amazon heavily targeted law enforcement as a client for Rekognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;ACLU took Amazon&amp;#39;s facial recognition tech—which Amazon is aggressively selling to police—and loaded it with 25,000 mugshots. Then, they ran photos of members of Congress against the mugshots. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;They got 28 matches, 40% of them Congressmen of color. &lt;a href="https://t.co/Wix11Z3poY"&gt;https://t.co/Wix11Z3poY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Trevor Timm (@trevortimm) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/trevortimm/status/1022498711157407745?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;July 26, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the ACLU raised several questions about the technology. One of the questions focused on how the system was built upon problematic data, namely a database of 25,000 public arrest photos. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Datasets like mugshots &lt;a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/facial-recognition-systems-racism-protests-police-bias/"&gt;are widely known to be biased&lt;/a&gt; as they do not accurately reflect the makeup of the broader United States population. Specifically this data overrepresents BIPOC people. Also, the image quality of mugshots themselves are suspect and can often be of poor qaulity. 
Combined with other problems, like &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2018/jul/26/amazon-facial-rekognition-congress-mugshots-aclu"&gt;a higher false positive rate identifying BIPOC as offenders&lt;/a&gt; and general problems of low accuracy the use of facial recognition in policing is again in the public limelight. The renewed focus on the Black Lives Matter movement and police brtuality has led to big tech companies like &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/recode/2020/6/10/21287194/amazon-microsoft-ibm-facial-recognition-moratorium-police"&gt;IBM, Amazon, and Microsoft stepping back - albeit temporarily - from selling facial recognition for law enforcement&lt;/a&gt;. 
While facial recognition technology may be temporarily unavailable to law enforcement, there are several other questions we as technologists should be grappling with. The availability of a technology is only a part of the discussion,  the other problems to be discussed lies in the application of how this technology will be used. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How facial recognition technology can be weaponized by policing, this will not be a uniform experience to all people. It will be informed by our social location - our race, our gender, our age, our area of residence. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chicago: A Segregated City&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take Chicago as an example. Labeled at times the United State's most segregated city, this 2015 CMAP &lt;a href="https://www.cmap.illinois.gov/updates/all/-/asset_publisher/UIMfSLnFfMB6/content/race-and-ethnicity-in-the-cmap-region"&gt;built with 2010 - 2014 American Community Survey data&lt;/a&gt; shows us with data just how segregated the city it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="max-width: 400px, display: center"&gt;
    &lt;img src="theme/images/cmap-2014.png" style="max-width: 100%, height:auto, width:auto, display: block"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The segregated landscape of Chicago is no accident. Instead we can understand Chicago as the result of decades, even centuries, of systemic racism and oppression.
One policy that clearly demonstrates the intentional remapping of Chicago's communities can be seen in &lt;a href="https://www.wbez.org/stories/new-redlining-maps-show-chicago-housing-discrimination/37c0dce7-0562-474a-8e1c-50948219ecbb"&gt;redlining&lt;/a&gt;. As a fiscal policy, redlining operated by labeling Chicago community areas on a scale from the "best" places for investment to the worst, or most "hazardous", places for investment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="max-width: 400px, display: center"&gt;
    &lt;img src="theme/images/redlining.jpg" style="max-width: 100%, height:auto, width:auto, display: block"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 1930s and 1940s the federal Home Owners' Loan Corporation, backed by the Federal Housing Authority (FHA), used this practice of labeling communities of color - largely Black communities - overwhemlingly as red, or "hazardous". The "hazardous" labeling meant that in these areas loans were not extended. As these loans were backed by the FHA, &lt;a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2014/06/the-case-for-reparations/361631/"&gt;the loans had a low interest rate and required a smaller down payment for purchasing a home&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally these loans became the economic catalyst used by &lt;a href="http://dspace.calstate.edu/bitstream/handle/10211.3/180032/Erika.EmeryDissertation.pdf?sequence=4"&gt;white America to finance their dreams of sending their children to college&lt;/a&gt;. Redlining is but one example demonstrating how divestment, informed by race and other socioeconomic factors, had the intended result of moving wealth out of BIPOC communities. Wealth that, while moving out of BIPOC communities, was concentrated in white communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My Chicago is not your Chicago&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systemic racism however is not only experienced in housing. Policing is intrinsically connected to housing as is wealth. Areas where police are deployed, or are not deployed, the way that policing happens; how one person experiences policing is greatly informed by the hyperlocal conditions on the ground as well as one's identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some quick stats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thetrace.org/2016/12/murder-inequality-neighborhood-homicide-rates/"&gt;Chicago's South and West sides are the community areas with the highest homicide rates&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chiyouthjustice.files.wordpress.com/2015/11/arresting-justice_facebook.jpg"&gt;Most of the arrests in a given year are BIPOC&lt;/a&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most police deployed in the highest crime Chicago community areas are &lt;a href="https://www.themarshallproject.org/2016/09/20/the-most-dangerous-neighborhood-the-most-inexperienced-cops"&gt;also the most inexperienced&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the areas hardest hit by COVID19 are &lt;a href="https://abc7chicago.com/coronavirus-illinois-chicago-black-deaths/6203131/"&gt;overwhemingly BIPOC communities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="max-width: 400px, display: center"&gt;
    &lt;img src="theme/images/covid19-zip.png" style="max-width: 100%, height:auto, width:auto, display: block"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why should we care about systems of oppression? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we as technologists build tools, we are not building technology in a vacuum. We do not build them devoid of the bias in the world around us. Nor do we fully have control over the way our tools will be employed.
It is our moral imperative to question not only how our technology is built, but why we need it. If the tools we create are based on the social landscape we live in, our tools merely "codigy the past". That is, we as technologists should not presume that our techology can, "invent the future" as author and activst &lt;a href="https://weaponsofmathdestructionbook.com/"&gt;Cathy O'Neil warns us&lt;/a&gt;. "Doing that requires moral imagination, and that's something only humans can provide".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am calling on you all to take time to educate yourself and understand how technology intersects with bias, with systems of power, and systems of inequity.
I've started a bias and equity in technology reading list that I will be reading through as well as 
soliciting feedback on. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="max-width: 400px, display: center"&gt;
    &lt;img src="theme/images/reading-list.JPG" style="max-width: 100%, height:auto, width:auto"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a suggestion that should be added to the list you can add 👉 &lt;a href="https://biasin.tech"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have to do the work. To show up. To listen. To learn. To stay engaged. Will you join me?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="inclusion"></category><category term="diversity"></category><category term="bias"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="equity"></category></entry><entry><title>Donate to your local community bond fund</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/donate-to-your-local-community-bond-fund.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2020-05-31:/donate-to-your-local-community-bond-fund.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;👋🏽,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a minute ⌚ since I wrote. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; are taking life day by day. Hour by hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the last 36 hours have been some of the most ... extreme …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;👋🏽,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a minute ⌚ since I wrote. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; are taking life day by day. Hour by hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the last 36 hours have been some of the most ... extreme. While I write this I hear the helicopters overhead, the honking down the block, the news in the background defaming my beautiful Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's so many emotions I know we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are angry. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are lusting for a life before COVID19. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want to be back together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cannot, as a light skinned person of Latinx heritage, justify sitting by on the sidelines while there are those that tell us &lt;em&gt;we should not care&lt;/em&gt;, that &lt;em&gt;we should do nothing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not &lt;strong&gt;ANGRY&lt;/strong&gt; at the &lt;em&gt;murder&lt;/em&gt; of George Floyd, at the countless black lives lost before, and what is likely to be the continued callous murders of our black brothers and sisters. I do not know what to say to you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not &lt;strong&gt;ANGRY&lt;/strong&gt; at your brown brother and sisters, many from Latin America, locked in cages and treated inhumanly. I do not know what to say to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not &lt;strong&gt;ANGRY&lt;/strong&gt; at billionaires getting richer while millions of USA people lose their jobs and income. I do not know what to say to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step up, be present, be critical. Most importantly, to my white people, listen. Listen, do something, &lt;strong&gt;DO BETTER, BE BETTER&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a way to start 👇🏽&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://chicagobond.org/donate/"&gt;DONATE MONEY TO THE CHICAGO COMMUNITY BOND FUND&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Donate &lt;a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/bail_funds_george_floyd"&gt;to your all the bond funds&lt;/a&gt; through this campaign. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🖖🏽, &amp;amp; 🐍, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lore is out.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="activism"></category></entry><entry><title>Akwaaba! A Pan-African Python Conference and The Year of Return</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/akwaaba-a-pan-african-python-conference-and-the-year-of-return.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-08-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-08-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2019-08-14:/akwaaba-a-pan-african-python-conference-and-the-year-of-return.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I returned from my first trip to West Africa visiting Lagos, Nigeria and Accra, Ghana. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In preparation for the trip, I had to obtain not one but two visas …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I returned from my first trip to West Africa visiting Lagos, Nigeria and Accra, Ghana. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In preparation for the trip, I had to obtain not one but two visas. In previous travels I've been able to obtain a visa at the airport such as when I visited Cuba in 2016. This time around I was strongly discouraged from obtaining a visa at the airport for various reasons including, it just may take many many hours. Acquiring two visas, one which required me to travel to New York City to submit my biometrics for the Nigerian tourist visa, in hindsight was a perfect prelude to my travel to West Africa. The privilege of not needing to consider what paperwork was needed prior to entry is a rare one and one I have been accustomed to. Time and time again I would be reminded of my privilege and how that informs the way I navigate the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Pan-African Python Conference: PyCon Africa&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, thanks where thanks are due. If it weren't for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/marlene_zw"&gt;Marlene Mhangami&lt;/a&gt;, a fellow Director of the Python Software Foundation, who also served as Chair for the inaugural &lt;a href="https://africa.pycon.org/"&gt;PyCon Africa&lt;/a&gt; I would not have attended PyCon Africa. It was Marlene who informed me, "you know, Accra and Lagos are about an hour flight apart" as my initials plans only included Lagos for a friend’s birthday celebration. (Please watch this 23 questions with Marlene video below, it's amazing!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&amp;quot;What&amp;#39;s your favorite Ghanaian food so far?&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I asked Marlene Mhangami (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/marlene_zw?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@marlene_zw&lt;/a&gt;) her 23.3 Questions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Marlene Mhangami is a Director and Communications Co-Chair of the Python Software Foundation from Zimbabwe.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Full video available to watch now at &lt;a href="https://t.co/Va8jh3u2GB"&gt;https://t.co/Va8jh3u2GB&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/iFajjb2nXR"&gt;pic.twitter.com/iFajjb2nXR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nkansah Rexford (@nkansahrexford) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nkansahrexford/status/1161401270403567619?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 13, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the &lt;a href="https://africa.pycon.org/team/"&gt;PyCon Africa organizing team&lt;/a&gt; is the same team behind &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconghana?lang=en"&gt;PyCon Ghana&lt;/a&gt;. These folks helped organize transport for international travelers to and from airport as well as coordinate countless details on the ground. Shout out to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/plasmadray"&gt;Noah Alorwu&lt;/a&gt; who graciously picked me up from the Accra airport and had the chance to observe the eccentricities of a person who has barely slept after ~ 14 hours of air travel! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;We love you Ghana, We love you Python Communities. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PlasmaDray?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@PlasmaDray&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PyConNA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@PyConNA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PythonNamibia?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@PythonNamibia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/nWh9JxhPUn"&gt;pic.twitter.com/nWh9JxhPUn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ngazetungue Muheue (@muheuenga) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/muheuenga/status/1160299806255960064?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 10, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kicking off with a day tour of Accra for international travelers and workshops like Django Girls, the core conference began on Thursday August 8th. I arrived in time from Lagos for the end of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Moustapha_6C"&gt;Moustapha Cisse&lt;/a&gt;'s, lead of Accra's Google AI team, opening keynote. Moustapha's keynote set a theme that'd continue to emerge for the rest of the conference: how can technology be used to solve African problems by African technologists? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Hello!!! Good Morning from Accra &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Ghana?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Ghana&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;br&gt;Some are already here, others from all over the world are starting to make their journeys to Accra. &lt;br&gt;Safe travels to all the pioneers who are going to be part of the first &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica19&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/FtEt237Hih"&gt;pic.twitter.com/FtEt237Hih&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Pycon Africa (@pyconafrica) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica/status/1158310099875782656?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 5, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The keynote expanded into an impromptu "ask me anything" session split 50/50 with the audience asking Moustapha questions followed by Moustapha asking questions of us. One telling question arose when Moustapha, whose work focuses on fairness, transparency and reliability in machine learning, was asked, "What problems do we confront [in machine learning] given the numerous amount of languages in Africa?". (Earlier Moustapha had indicated that the lack of data in African languages has been a barrier in creating machine learning solutions that work adequately for Africa.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;“Another challenge for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/machinelearning?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#machinelearning&lt;/a&gt; [in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Africa?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Africa&lt;/a&gt;@is the lack of data] in local languages,” &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Moustapha_6C?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Moustapha_6C&lt;/a&gt; on the future of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/machinelearning?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#machinelearning&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Africa?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Africa&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena 🐯 &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; 🐯 Mesa @ The Cosmos 💫 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1159421524102672389?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;There are 2,000+ languages in Africa. It’s the most linguistically diverse place in the world. Machine learning is being used to help reduce the linguistic barriers. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Moustapha Cisse, Head of Google AI Center Accra, is dropping knowledge!&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/KojoInACC?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#KojoInACC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kojo Idrissa @ Home #NorAmGT (@Transition) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Transition/status/1159415836085374976?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to the question, Moustapha summarized "it's not a problem, but a wealth" to have such an abundance of African languages adding that, "access to information is not unique to Africa but is true for the entire world". Digging deeper, Moustapha outlined two approaches to solving NLP problems like language detection, stating that he was most interested in deep learning as deep learning, unlike statistical ML solutions, doesn't rely on human translation and language expertise. When solving African problems, the focus should not be on deficiencies but on the wealth of the African community. "I myself am a failed physicist so I went to ML as it was simpler", Moustapha joked while asking the audience to consider "what triggered your curiosity to pursue the path into technology?".  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next two days several speakers continued to reiterate forms of this question, inspiring the audience to think creatively about what they can do for their communities. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/felipedemorais_"&gt;Felipe de Morais&lt;/a&gt;' talk on AfroPython, a Brasilian community he helps organize, explored this idea deeper, focusing on the role of diaspora for Afro-Brasilians. At one point, raising the challenge that, "&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1159438676486758402?s=20"&gt;you do not have to be Black to help Black people&lt;/a&gt;". The &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bright_morkli/status/1159506152784310276?s=20"&gt;African tech panel&lt;/a&gt; also challenged everyone to consider what it means to build a sustainable African tech economy. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JessicaUpani?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1159494805719851008&amp;amp;ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fpublish.twitter.com%2F%3Fquery%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Ftwitter.com%252Floooorenanicole%252Fstatus%252F1159494805719851008%26widget%3DTweet"&gt;Jessica Upani&lt;/a&gt;, a PyCon Namibia organizer, added to this noting that, "it is time we raise our own capital and not rely on others, what does the future look like for us?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="pt" dir="ltr"&gt;AFROPYTHON PELO MUNDO 🌍✨&lt;br&gt;⠀&lt;br&gt;Você sabia que o Brasil é o país com maior número de pessoas negras fora do continente africano? E olhem que interessante: o &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/felipedemorais_?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@felipedemorais_&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; esteve, nesta semana, em Accra, capital de Gana, falando sobre o AfroPython na primeira &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://t.co/qPGntjsVxf"&gt;pic.twitter.com/qPGntjsVxf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; AfroPython (@AfroPython) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AfroPython/status/1160872362881015808?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 12, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JessicaUpani?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@JessicaUpani&lt;/a&gt; session on &amp;quot;Is this Python thing really working&amp;quot; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/CwkyNiQ5Ab"&gt;pic.twitter.com/CwkyNiQ5Ab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Scholar Israel (@Scholarfiawo) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Scholarfiawo/status/1159488405731971073?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;“It is time we raise our own capital &amp;amp; not rely on others,” &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JessicaUpani?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@JessicaUpani&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PyConNA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@PyConNA&lt;/a&gt; shares adding, “what does the future look like for us?” &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Community building is taxing &amp;amp; thankless work, 💖 thank you &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JessicaUpani?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@JessicaUpani&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Python?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Python&lt;/a&gt; is better b/c of people like you. 💖&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena 🐯 &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; 🐯 Mesa @ The Cosmos 💫 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1159494805719851008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this future facing discussion culminated with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/transition"&gt;Kojo Idrissa&lt;/a&gt;'s emotionally powerful keynote that reflected on lessons from the past. Beginning with how his name is based on the famous Maroon leader &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cudjoe"&gt;Cudjoe&lt;/a&gt; to the simple truth that he has returned to Africa,  "Because my cousins has invited me home" both to PyCon Africa and through &lt;a href="http://yearofreturn.com"&gt;The Year of Return&lt;/a&gt;, Kojo spoke to how the legacy of the African diaspora has had an impact on us all, regardless of where one lives. It is up to us to choose how we will learn from it. For Kojo, he has chosen to use the empathy he has learned and feels to help build a more inclusive Python and by extension technical community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;“Why am I here? Because my cousins invited me home,” &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Transition?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Transition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;🎉🎉🎉&lt;br&gt;👏🏿👏🏿👏🏿&lt;br&gt;🔥🔥🔥&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; 🌍 &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/1JeLLnvlwW"&gt;pic.twitter.com/1JeLLnvlwW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena 🐯 &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; 🐯 Mesa @ The Cosmos 💫 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1159880011752660993?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 9, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/pyconafrica2019?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#pyconafrica2019&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/pyconafrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt; had 4 wonderful keynote speakers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thread&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Transition?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@Transition&lt;/a&gt; Kojo is a Board member of Django Events Foundation North America, and a software developer.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Kojo is based in Houston, Texas. &lt;a href="https://t.co/OBYsXIPggl"&gt;pic.twitter.com/OBYsXIPggl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; KhoPhi Photography (@KhoPhiPhotog) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KhoPhiPhotog/status/1161439240489771008?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 14, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Year of Return: Using the past to inform the future&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2019 marks the 400th anniversary of the arrival of the first enslaved Africans in Jamestown, Virginia. To commemorate this anniversary and to movie the narrative to one of Homecoming, the Ghana government kicked off 2019 as the &lt;a href="https://www.yearofreturn.com/about/"&gt;Year of Return&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Lest we never forget those countless Africans that lost their lives, their name, their identity, their right to be seen and treated as humans. 🇬🇭 &lt;a href="https://t.co/Km3ZozXePe"&gt;pic.twitter.com/Km3ZozXePe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena 🐯 &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; 🐯 Mesa @ The Cosmos 💫 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1160589904054751234?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 11, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nigeria at approximately 200 million people is the most populous African country with &lt;a href="https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ni.html"&gt;42.54% of the population under 14&lt;/a&gt;. Training centers like Andela that are “harder to get into than Harvard” (in 2016 they received &lt;a href="https://andela.com/insights/year-look-past-12-months/"&gt;23,400 applications and only had a 0.6% acceptance rate&lt;/a&gt;!) combined with other bold initiatives like &lt;a href="datasciencenigeria.org"&gt;Data Science Nigeria’s&lt;/a&gt; effort to “raising 1 million AI talents in 10 years” are but a small reflection of the vast untapped talent in Africa. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The many people I met at PyCon Africa (and in my trip in general), from Benin to Zimbabwe, emparted upon me a valuable lesson: it isn’t the past that dictates the future but how we use that past to build the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will the world engage with the African tech community? How will those within Africa engage with one another? And ultimately, how can we all as Pythonistas or generally speaking as technologists do better? Time will tell, but already change is in the air and I for one am excited for the future. Oh and you should go to PyCon Africa 2020, I know I'll be there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Well &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; was amazing. Met so many fantastic people in such a short space of time. Such a colourful community in so many ways. &lt;br&gt;Photo credit &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nkansahrexford?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@nkansahrexford&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/je1NrNT1nv"&gt;pic.twitter.com/je1NrNT1nv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anthony Shaw (アントニー・ショー) (@anthonypjshaw) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anthonypjshaw/status/1160648246739574784?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 11, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;I’ve made it to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt;!!!!! So excited to meet you all please come say hi if you’re attending!! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/vMeG1j7EGT"&gt;pic.twitter.com/vMeG1j7EGT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena 🐯 &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; 🐯 Mesa @ The Cosmos 💫 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1159419061509300225?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 8, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;A group of eager and ready &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Pythonistas?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#Pythonistas&lt;/a&gt; looking for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pyconafrica?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@pyconafrica&lt;/a&gt; Day Two to start! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@ewa_jodlowska&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PlasmaDray?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@PlasmaDray&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/_the_ike?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@_the_ike&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ThePSF?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@ThePSF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; 🌍 🌍 🌍 &lt;a href="https://t.co/ZsaSjyM8B7"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZsaSjyM8B7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Loooorena 🐯 &amp;quot;La Tigresa&amp;quot; 🐯 Mesa @ The Cosmos 💫 (@loooorenanicole) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/loooorenanicole/status/1159761566931329024?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 9, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Thank you organizers! It’s been a wonderful and emotional experience. EVERYONE should try to get to PyCon Africa 2020. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/PyConAfrica?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#PyConAfrica&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/pPtDEx9DL7"&gt;pic.twitter.com/pPtDEx9DL7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ewa Jodlowska (@ewa_jodlowska) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ewa_jodlowska/status/1159900840846487552?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;August 9, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Python"></category><category term="Africa"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="AI"></category><category term="ML"></category><category term="travel"></category></entry><entry><title>My checklist to hosting an inclusive event</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/my-checklist-to-hosting-an-inclusive-event.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-07-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2019-07-27:/my-checklist-to-hosting-an-inclusive-event.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having been a community organizer in several regards over the years, a common question I am asked is "How do I run an event?". To which I respond, "Here is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having been a community organizer in several regards over the years, a common question I am asked is "How do I run an event?". To which I respond, "Here is how I run an inclusive event". My intent is not to sound smart when I insert the emphasis on inclusivity, but to highlight inclusivity as the overarching theme when building community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What do I mean when I say inclusivity?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we discuss inclusivity, you may hear it bundled in such phrases as "diversity and inclusion" or "diversity, inclusion, and belonging". Inclusivity, as I understand it, cannot occur without consideration to the diversity or belonging of its community members. Inclusivity relies on both the rich, diverse backgrounds (e.g. ethnicity, country of origin, language, sexuality) of its members but more importantly on the extent that those members have a sense of acceptance and belonging. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it in other terms, "diversity is being invited to the party, inclusion is being asked to dance" (as I heard it described at PyCon Colombia 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Community building begins with inclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a list of things I have developed over the years, with the full acknowledgement that some of these at times can be aspirational:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host at a venue that &lt;a href="https://www.adachecklist.org/doc/fullchecklist/ada-checklist.pdf"&gt;ADA compliant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure presenters create presentations with &lt;a href="https://github.com/A11YChi/A11Y-Presentations"&gt;accessibility in mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Require that the host venue use RSVPed names bypassing the need to use &lt;a href="https://www.healthline.com/health/transgender/deadnaming"&gt;a name on an ID&lt;/a&gt; (as these are often out of sync anyway)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a clearly placed &lt;a href="https://geekfeminism.wikia.org/wiki/Code_of_conduct_evaluations"&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt; on the community page (e.g. see our &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/Chicago-PyLadies/"&gt;about section&lt;/a&gt;), kicking off each event with a reminder to the Code of Conduct and to seek organizers if there are any questions/concerns/feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce myself at the start of each event with my name and &lt;a href="http://feministing.com/2015/02/03/how-using-they-as-a-singular-pronoun-can-change-the-world/"&gt;pronouns&lt;/a&gt; (ideally having some mechanism for attendees to mark pronouns such as on name tags if worn) to set community norms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I highly recommend that all organizers participate in a Code of Conduct training, learning how to respond to incident reports and brainstorming ways to develop procedure if one is lacking or incomplete. There are several groups, such as &lt;a href="https://otter.technology/code-of-conduct-training/"&gt;Otter Tech&lt;/a&gt;, that offer training as well as &lt;a href="https://geekfeminism.wikia.org/wiki/Conference_anti-harassment"&gt;many resources available online&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are seeking likeminded organizers to discuss inclusivity with the &lt;a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Diversity_and_Inclusion_for_Communities_and_Contributors"&gt;Mozilla Diverstiy and Inclusion for COmmunities and Contributors group&lt;/a&gt; is a rich community with an email list for discussion and semi-frequent scheduled calls to discuss specific topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How we can do better?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As inclusivisity is always a work in progress, I actively solicit feedback by asking, "How can we do better?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What tools, community norms and practices, requirements do you use when hosting an inclusive event? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, how can we do better?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="inclusion"></category><category term="inclusivity"></category><category term="community-building"></category><category term="diversity"></category><category term="belonging"></category></entry><entry><title>Building a GitHub page with Pelican, a Python static site generator</title><link href="https://lorenamesa.com/building-a-github-page-with-pelican-a-python-static-site-generator.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-08-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Lorena Mesa</name></author><id>tag:lorenamesa.com,2018-08-28:/building-a-github-page-with-pelican-a-python-static-site-generator.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've ever wanted to quickly spin up a personal website but, like me, are either preoccupied with design or want something basic to help you get started look no …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you've ever wanted to quickly spin up a personal website but, like me, are either preoccupied with design or want something basic to help you get started look no further. Static site generators are a great way to help you build a website if:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you want to use a predefined css/html template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don't want to deal with a complicated dynamic CMS like Wordpress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;want a page that will be served up fast!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;are looking to add version control to your content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code behind my website is powered by &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a Python static website generator. If you are curious about other static website generators, there are various &lt;a href="https://www.creativebloq.com/features/10-best-static-site-generators"&gt;lists&lt;/a&gt; on the web that you can easily find with a Google search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do I build a website with Pelican?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, I'll cover how to build a GitHub page website with Pelican that is hosted on (surprise surprise) GitHub. Additionally we'll review how to add version control to your GitHub repo that maintains the website content, the website theme, and Pelican code in separate repos. Lastly, we'll deploy the code to the GitHub page and even customize the GitHub page with a domain name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll likely want to clone a copy &lt;a href="https://github.com/lorenanicole/lorenanicole.github.io-src"&gt;my repo&lt;/a&gt; to follow along with the code snippets in this post. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download the code to your machine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git clone --recursive repo-url  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# downloads the submodules&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;What's in the repo?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master (&lt;code&gt;lorenanicole.github.io-src&lt;/code&gt;) repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;/output&lt;/code&gt; dir points to &lt;a href="https://github.com/lorenanicole/lorenannicole.github.io"&gt;my GitHub pages repo&lt;/a&gt; where Pelican builds and stores generated static files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;'/voce' dir points to &lt;a href="https://github.com/lorenanicole/voce"&gt;fork of the Pelican theme voce&lt;/a&gt; used in my website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find more Pelican themes explore &lt;a href="http://www.pelicanthemes.com/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need help configuring your own Pelican repos? Read &lt;a href="https://fedoramagazine.org/make-github-pages-blog-with-pelican/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Generating content&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pelican theme (in this case &lt;code&gt;voce&lt;/code&gt;) has templates that define the design of the website. The customizations for configuring a Pelican website are found in the &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt; file in this repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create content add a Markdown or RST file with the name of the page or article you'd like to create. Markdown, as used in this repo, will need to be installed via &lt;code&gt;pip install Markdown&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write an article create a &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.rst&lt;/code&gt; file in the &lt;code&gt;/content/articles&lt;/code&gt; directory. You'll need to specify a title at a minimum, other attributes can be found here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write a page, again create create a &lt;code&gt;.md&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.rst&lt;/code&gt; file, this time in the &lt;code&gt;/content/pages&lt;/code&gt; directory. Again you need to specify minimum metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your pages (the site navigation sections defined in the menu) or articles (e.g. blog posts) are created you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;make html &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; make serve  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Exports static pages/articles to /output and serves locally&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If all looks good you can: &lt;code&gt;make publish&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;make html&lt;/code&gt; but ensure your &lt;code&gt;SITE_URL&lt;/code&gt; is set to not to &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /output
git remote -v  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ensure points to the github page repo&lt;/span&gt;
git add 
git commit -m &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;new pages&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
git push
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;code&gt;yourusername.github.io&lt;/code&gt; to see the changes real time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an entire overview of getting started with Pelican read the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.1.1/getting_started.html"&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How do you add your own domain to your github page?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to add a &lt;code&gt;CNAME&lt;/code&gt; file with your domain name in your github pages repo. Additionally you'll need to configure your DNS record on your domain provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples tutorials:
- &lt;a href="http://spector.io/how-to-set-up-github-pages-with-a-custom-domain-on-gandi/"&gt;Gandi + GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;
- &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@supriyakankure/how-to-add-a-custom-domain-to-your-github-page-with-godaddy-84495781143e"&gt;GoDaddy + GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Questions?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please reach out! All my contact info is in the menu above. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="github-page"></category></entry></feed>